Your first program in Sanskrita — in just five minutes. Let's begin!
संस्कृता में अपना पहला प्रोग्राम — सिर्फ़ पाँच मिनट में। चलिए, शुरू करते हैं!
You need just two things — Python 3, already on most computers, and our GitHub repo.
चाहिए बस दो चीज़ें — Python 3, जो ज़्यादातर कंप्यूटर में पहले से होता है, और हमारा GitHub repo।
Open the Terminal. First clone the repo, then type — bash install.sh.
Terminal खोलिए। पहले repo को clone कीजिए, फिर लिखिए — bash install.sh।
That's it! Sanskrita is ready.
बस! संस्कृता तैयार है।
Now create a file — नमस्ते.सं. And write in it — वद("नमस्ते जगत्")।
अब एक फ़ाइल बनाइए — नमस्ते.सं। और उसमें लिखिए — वद("नमस्ते जगत्")।
Don't forget the danda । at the end!
अंत में दण्ड । लगाना मत भूलिए!
Now run it — sanskrita नमस्ते.सं. And look — your first Sanskrit program just spoke!
अब चलाइए — sanskrita नमस्ते.सं। और देखिए — आपका पहला संस्कृत प्रोग्राम बोल उठा!
Devanagari typing feels hard? No problem. Run sanskrita-playground — type in roman letters, and it becomes Devanagari automatically!
देवनागरी type करना मुश्किल लगे? कोई बात नहीं। sanskrita-playground चलाइए — roman में type कीजिए, अपने आप देवनागरी बन जाएगी!
What next? The repo has a full tutorial — ten programs in an hour. Plus the AI-SPEC — turn any AI into your personal Sanskrita guru!
और आगे? repo में पूरा tutorial है — दस प्रोग्राम, एक घंटे में। साथ में AI-SPEC भी — किसी भी AI को अपना संस्कृता-गुरु बनाइए!
So write your first program today — post it on GitHub and tell us! Jayatu Sanskritam!
तो आज ही अपना पहला प्रोग्राम लिखिए — और GitHub पर post करके हमें ज़रूर बताइए। जयतु संस्कृतम्!